<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second admonition, sent by the subdued prouinces to Holland thereby to entice them by faire-seeming reasons, groundlesse threates, and vnlike examples to make peace with the Spaniards. With the Hollanders aunswere to the same. Translated out of Dutch into English by H.W.</title>
            <title>Second admonition, sent by the subdued provinces to Holland.</title>
            <author>Netherlands.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105504</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841232</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841232</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5796</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08107)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5796)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 557:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second admonition, sent by the subdued prouinces to Holland thereby to entice them by faire-seeming reasons, groundlesse threates, and vnlike examples to make peace with the Spaniards. With the Hollanders aunswere to the same. Translated out of Dutch into English by H.W.</title>
                  <title>Second admonition, sent by the subdued provinces to Holland.</title>
                  <author>Netherlands.</author>
                  <author>H. W., fl. 1598.</author>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by [I. Windet for] Iohn Wolfe, and are to bee sold at his shoppe within the Popes head Alley in Lombard street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Print show-through; some leaves tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Belgium --  History --  1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5796:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5796:1"/>
            <p>THE SECOND Admonition, Sent by the ſubdued Prouinces to Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, thereby to entice them by faire-ſeeming rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, groundleſſe threates, and vnlike ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to make peace with the Spaniards.</p>
            <p>With the Hollanders aunſwere to <hi>the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Dutch into Engliſh by H. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by <hi>Iohn Wolfe,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhoppe within the Popes head Alley in Lombard ſtreet 1598.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5796:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5796:2"/>
            <head>To Holland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Eace, O peace, O ſwéeteſt eſtate, neuer was a ſwéeter word heard. Peace enemy to ſtrife, contention and reuenge, thée I ſéeke and deſire from the bottome of my heart: thou art the moſt precious iewell that euer was found, the ſpring of welfare and delight. Thou healeſt that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie hath wounded. Thou cauſeſt the ſcattered thinges to be relyed. Thou cauſeſt and createſt ioy and pleaſure in euery place. Where peace is, there are our yeares doubled: there life is long, and all our life is ſwéet: there is riches and plentie at full: there fortune is not ſéene ſo vnſtedfaſt. Thou art the treaſure where all good is inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the beautifying of the worlde, to whome all honor is due by common accord.</p>
            <q>Happie are they that ſeeke peace ſayth the word of the Lord.</q>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2.</head>
               <p>PEace dwelleth in the kingdome of God. Peace Chriſt hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended vnto all beléeuers. With peace are gloriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded and ſwéetly crowned Gods people. Peace is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall teſtament which the Lord before his death bequeathed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended vs. Peace is the bond &amp; perfect image, where through wee deſerue the heauens, and without peace all woulde vaniſh to nought, for through diſcord each thing decayeth. Peace hindreth deſtruction, deſolation, and griefe. Peace makes kingdomes and countries to flouriſh. Peace is euery where greatly eſtéemed: na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture forceth all men to loue peace. And what is there more delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then peace, to agrée and continue in amitie to the end.</p>
               <q>Wo to him who is a friend to ſtrife.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3.</head>
               <p>THou O Peace art pleaſing vnto all nations, and full of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, yet neuertheleſſe in theſe broyles, we ſée thée inhumane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5796:3"/>
excluded out of the Hollandiſh limites. Whence doth this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede O <hi>Hollandia</hi>? inſooth it is a ſtrange matter, that thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the thing which euery one naturally deſireth. Art thou blind? art thou ſo ſenceleſſe that thou chuſeſt mortail poyſon rather then daintie and exquiſite food? wilt thou neuer riſe out of this thy obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and lay aſide this pernitious diſcord. Thou art like vnto a ſicke perſon, or the frantike, which madly reiect the good and hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome thinges proffered them. Compare the paſſed time vnto the preſent, before thou didſt reiect thy obeyſance, was it not farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then to liue in this ſort imothered in ſtrife and contention, and like beaſtes ſhedding the blood of thy members?</p>
               <q>Where peace is hated no mercie can dwell.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4.</head>
               <p>THou art moleſted and pilled with taxations, and giueſt the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier the ſubſtance, whereon thy people ſhoulde liue. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon trafficke doth melt and conſume, for it muſt be vſed with force and might. And as long while as thou doeſt embrace this peſtife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous contention, thou ſhalt find no reſt nor quiet in no place: yea finally euery one will forſake thée: for all <hi>Europe</hi> (for thy ſake) endureth great miſerie, thou muſt know that each thing hath but his time, and thy doing cannot continue long. Oh that thou wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt once conſider thy owne good, thy hart woulde turne and bee moued. What profit is it alwayes to continue the warres? what pleaſure in miſchéeuing one another? thy ſucceſſors ſhal hereafter feele the ſmart, vnleſſe thou change thy hate</p>
               <q>One otfen knoweth his fault, but repenteth too late.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5.</head>
               <p>ACcept peace, beléeue the counſaile of thy friends: bow ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what thy head, and ceaſe thy obſtinacie: reiect paſſion who bereaueth the fences, and apalleth the ſpirit, but let his light ſhine. Peace is at hande if thou canſt but affect her. Thy Prince (O <hi>Holland</hi>) is neither rigorous nor cruell. I fought be paſſed which any greeue thée, thinke thy ſelfe hath béene cauſe thereof, each
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5796:3"/>
thing may eaſily be amended, if in caſe thou wilt be ruled by reaſon, his lappe is open, his goodneſſe is readie, ſéeke peace, and all will be well: Thou ſhalt be holpe, appeaſed and diſburthened, and fedde as a limme of the patrimony: Turne to thy wonted obedience, acknowledge thy ſuperiors.</p>
               <q>All ſhalbe well, and things paſt forgotten.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>6.</head>
               <p>TIs time, tis time, that thou ſhouldeſt perceiue thine owne wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and haſten to peace before it waxe too late, for although thou doeſt abound in wealth and content, whereof thy courage ſwelleth, yet think how others in like caſe haue béene ſerued when they refuſed the peace, tis wiſedome to take occaſion when it is proffered, and helpe himſelfe with fortune when ſhe ſmileth. The Athenians becauſe they once ſubdued and gouerned the Spartans,<note place="margin">Athens.</note> thought to gouerne all with their might, and would hearken to no peace, but what happened vnto thoſe which they thought to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, they became their ſubiects. This is the worldes courſe in all humaine affaires, which to day exalt, and to morrow wil make a ſlaue.</p>
               <q>Wiſe is he who at others harmes doth warning take.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>7.</head>
               <p>WHen the vnwiſe Romains reiected the ſwéet peace which <hi>Caeſar</hi> kindly offered them,<note place="margin">Rome.</note> and that (as the hiſtorie ſaith) <hi>Pompeius</hi> with his armies thought to withſtand <hi>Caeſars</hi> might, a fire was kindled, which conſumed the earth and ruined <hi>Rome</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mightie people loſt his former libertie: <hi>Pompey</hi> was murthered, and all the nobilitie ſubdued: and in that ſort that monarchy which whilome ruled and ſwayed ouer the world was ſubdued &amp; brought to nought, where (if they had accepted peace) they might haue continued in their former eſtate. Conſider this, the time is the manifeſter of all hidden things, marke then what profit occaſion well taken doth bring.</p>
               <q>Vnwiſe is he who the vncertaine before the ſure doth prefer.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:5796:4"/>
               <head>8</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Carthage.</note>ALſo if <hi>Carthage</hi> had helde, and not violated the true peace which was granted them by <hi>Fabius,</hi> they might very well haue ſhunned the deſtruction which after befell them, when the Romaines the ſecond time raiſed their ſtandardes againſt them. Had <hi>Mithridates</hi> accepted the alliance which was kindly proffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him,<note place="margin">Mithridates.</note> he had neuer fallen into thoſe daungers, nor in the wars which dured fortie yeares, but becauſe he could not fancie peace, he ſpoiled his kingdome &amp; loſt his life.<note place="margin">Iugurtha</note> Alſo had not <hi>Iugurtha</hi> through euill counſaile reiected the peace offered him, hee had neuer béene caryed captiue to <hi>Rome,</hi> where hee ended his life in miſerie and thrail.</p>
               <q>He neuer fared well, that on the warre him founded.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>9.</head>
               <p>WHen <hi>Iſrael</hi> departed out of the deſerts, trauelling with great paine towardes the land of promiſe, they reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted king <hi>Sehon</hi> to let them paſſe peaceably,<note place="margin">Sehon.</note> they not deſiring to hurt his realme, but he proud and vnwiſe rather choſe warre, then peace with loue, wherefore obſtinacie had her reward, being cauſe that he loſt both kingdome and life. Alſo when the Beniamites e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill minded,<note place="margin">Beniamites.</note> had ſinned and diſturbed all Iſrael, might at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the broyles with ſmall amends haue ceaſed the warres, but no, they came into the field againſt their brethren, by which they were pittifully diſcomfited, and 25000. of them were ſlayne, and their Cittie burnt all within thrée daies.</p>
               <q>Hee that neglecteth occaſion proffered, needes not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>10.</head>
               <p>NEuer had béene ſéene the heapes of murthered Troianes and flouds of their blood, nor yet that flouriſhing kingdome ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the valiant Gréekes, who at the firſt proffered them condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of peace, but alas they were bereaued of their former wittes,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5796:4"/>
not being able to loue peace. Had eke the victorious Perſian <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> accepted the peace in <hi>Scithia,</hi> which <hi>Tomyris</hi> ſonne proffered him, he had not béen diſcomfited and ſlain in that vnluckie battaile, where all his hoſte (though great) was put to the ſworde, and his ſeuered head was (by <hi>Tomiris</hi>) bathed in his owne blood, O miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous and vnluckie chance. But yet more, O the miſchieuous and wicked workes of men which do cauſe them.</p>
               <q>He that is prouident, may beware in time.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>11.</head>
               <p>THe Citie of <hi>Siracuſa</hi> ſo highly renowned, that ſhe was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>Carthage,</hi> is not ſhe likewiſe come to the like miſhap,<note place="margin">Siracuſe.</note> and by the warre pittifully ſpoyled? for they alſo reiected the peace which <hi>Marcelles</hi> was willing to giue them, they ſtood very ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon their inſtruments, which <hi>Archimedes</hi> made them, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall in the Romain Campe they did many wonderfull exploits to their aduantage, yet notwithſtanding their triple wall, all their couragious ſoldiers, nor yet their ſtrange deuiſes did any whit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite them againſt the Romaine wrath, but were ouerthrowne and made pillage, where they loſt both their honour, and fréedome.</p>
               <q>He that lets a good opotunitie eſcape, may after want it.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>12.</head>
               <p>HAd <hi>Iudea</hi> (when ſhe was kindled with anger and deſire to deliuer her ſelfe from the Romaine ſubiection) with proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhunned the perill which hung ouer her heade,<note place="margin">Iudea.</note> and learned to breake her high minded and rebellious courage, before <hi>Veſpatian</hi> came, who (as is known) brought them all into deſolation, ſhe had neuer felt that gréeuous ſmart, whereof whole hiſtories are ſcarce able to tell the miſerie: ſhe might haue had mercie &amp; béen conſerued, where to the contrarie ſhe hath aboade more miſerie then any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on earth. O how wiſe is he, who ſéeketh reſt and tranquillitie. why chuſe you the badde rather then the good? is not vnitie farre better then diſſention?</p>
               <q>What reaſon will not do, experience teacheth.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:5796:5"/>
               <head>13.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Coſroe.</note>THe king <hi>Coſroe</hi> that mightie potentate, who continually rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Perſian eſtate, had he kindly accepted the peace, which vnfaynedly was by the Emperour proffered, hee had had fortune ſo his wiſh, &amp; her whéele wold not ſo ſoone haue turned. <hi>Heraclius</hi> ſought peace, as the thing moſt beneficiall vnto both: but <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roe</hi> was therewithall not appaid, he thirſted after warre, and hee was ſuffiſed, with thrée ſundry battailes, which all went againſt him, had not he ſcorned the Emperors kindneſſe, &amp; refuſed peace, he had not had that reprochfull diſcomfiture, nor brought himſelfe and his people in that diſtreſſe. Marke then what negligence doth cauſe, when in time one cannot foreſee his owne good.</p>
               <q>What ſtrife doth ſpoyle, doth bind the peace.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>14.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1519. 1521.</note>HOw fared in old time the Spaniſh band, which alſo knew not their ſuperiors counſaile, they were offered peace to ende the broyles, but they rather choſe the warre, and the miſeries of the ſame which was the cauſe that they were perſecuted, baniſht and ſlaine, he who refuſeth peace proffered, doth not deſerue to haue it afterwardes.<note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ples. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a.</note> And how often haue the Neapolitaines béene di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed? Moreouer reade what of <hi>Frieſland</hi> is written for they being in ſtrife with the Saxons, refuſed peace: yea more came in the field with the Emperour. Wherefore O <hi>Holland</hi> take care to deale wiſely, accept peace, ſtrife hath endured enough.</p>
               <q>The whole bodie greeues at the diſcord of the limmes.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>15.</head>
               <p>BOth <hi>Cleueland</hi> and <hi>Gelderland</hi> can record what profite the warre bringes, when peace is refuſed, had they ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed their high mindes as they were counſayled, they had not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into the deſtruction which hath ruined all the land. Moreouer call to remembrance O <hi>Holland</hi> what iſſue the broiles in North
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5796:5"/>
                  <hi>Holland</hi> tooke,<note place="margin">North Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> when thy communaltie rebelliouſly were riſen vp againſt their Magiſtrates, and as enraged people ran about, all their mindes being bent to murther and bloodſhed, they alſo were proffered peace, but they deſirous to liue at libertie and rule all thinges to their owne fancie refuſed the ſame, where through at laſt they were well puniſhed for their fooliſh pretence.</p>
               <q>It ſeldome goes well where the people doth rule.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>16.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Friend, let this bee a looking glaſſe vnto thée, theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are manifeſt and knowne. Shunne ſtrife, and deſire peace: let none ſpare himſelfe to that ſwéet and delectable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, viſit thy prince, ſend thy ambaſſadors, not to nouriſh the warre, nor to exile peace, but endeuour thy ſelfe to vnity, for <hi>concordia</hi> is the ſwéeteſt treaſure on earth, thy neighbors and allies deſire the ſame, giue eare vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: thy ſuperiors expect thée and will heare thée, and their hearts are bent to thée, depart from this wicked reſiſtance, whereunto ſome counſaile thée, but the craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſubtill ſéeke more their owne profite thereby, then thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, or thy countries good. It is alwaies good fiſhing in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled water, and cutting broade girdles out of other mens leather.</p>
               <q>A fayned friend ought to be ſhunned as an enemie.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>17.</head>
               <p>THou art fedde with lies and diſſimulations, thou art perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to exclude the truth, and that thy vertues and praiſe ſhall be extolled in the places where the earth is full of veynes of gold, thou art euery where greatly eſtéemd, becauſe thou canſt ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily rule <hi>Mars</hi> himſelfe. In the Eaſt and North thy fame is ſpread, by reaſon whereof thou thinkeſt all the world will adore thée, thou perſuadeſt thy ſelfe to be inuincible, but ſurely it will faile thée, for God doth alwaies abate ſuch high minds: thou wilt neither ſtoop nor obay, but ſéekeſt to become a common wealth of ſome newe manner: conſider I pray what a man doth in his wantonneſſe when eaſe and pride hath poſſeſſed his heart: are all thy deedes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed?
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5796:6"/>
wilt thou no more harber after ſubiection.</p>
               <q>Where force is a counſailour, wiſdome is forgotten.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>18.</head>
               <p>BVt finally <hi>(Holland)</hi> thou ſhalt find thyne error: there were neuer yet found rebels, which in their faults were not confuted &amp; ouerthrowen, with plagues as is euery where ſeen and known: take examples in Gods houſe it ſelfe, where an Angell rayſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againſt the Almightie God, yea an Angell who in glory and beautie farre ſurpaſſed all the reſt, as ſcriptures do vnfolde, fell hee not and the reſt with an incurable wound? becauſe againſt their ſoueraigne they rebelled: from the moſt higheſt he was made the baſeſt, from the fayreſt to the ouglyeſt, from great glorie to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall confuſion: a ſhort pleaſure bringeth great griefe, an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to all ſubiectes.</p>
               <q>What rebellion winnes is no victorie.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>19.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iſraelites.</note>HOw often hath Iſrael beene plagued of God, brought in néed and chaſtiſed, when the commandement of <hi>Moyſes</hi> did not like them, and did ſtill tranſgreſſe the ſame: alſo how wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God puniſhed the 10. tribes which were rebelled from the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſeat &amp; ſubiection of <hi>Iuda.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Abſolon.</note> Alſo <hi>Abſolon</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his complices very ſhamefully roſe vp in armes againſt <hi>Dauid,</hi> and a thouſand others (too long to rehearſe) the which God hath puniſhed. Rebellion is an infection, a ſtinke, a thing hated, an ouerruled mallice, and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the picture and image of helliſh diſcord. A poyſon of a deadly compoſition, a tree bearing deadly fruit.</p>
               <q>A common wealth is ſpoyled where ſtrife is begunne.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>20.</head>
               <p>THe heathen hiſtories do alſo record how ſeuerely the Citie of <hi>Thebes</hi> in <hi>Grecia</hi> was puniſhed for her rebellion, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolted from the Macedonians, but they had loſſe in ſtead of profit,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5796:6"/>
and in ſtead of libertie were brought in more ſeruitude.<note place="margin">Capua. Numatia.</note> 
                  <hi>Capua</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo loſt her glorie, when ſhe began to rebell: how deare did <hi>Numa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> buy her fooliſh rebellion, and the Italian vaſſalles which roſe vp againſt the Romaine eſtate?<note place="margin">Bellum ſociale Bataui.</note> How fared the Batauians (thy firſt ſeede) in their rebellion during <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> raygne, the beginning was luckie, but the ende deſolate, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſhewes in his Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Chronicle.</p>
               <q>He that ſeekes to raiſe himſelfe falles often in the dirt.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>21.</head>
               <p>HOw much blood hath <hi>Italie</hi> ſhed when the enraged people ſet their mutinies abroach, and (as we finde written) the <hi>Germaine</hi> Emperor appeaſed them. What <hi>Germany</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured in that time, when <hi>Carolus Quintus</hi> raigned,<note place="margin">Germany.</note> is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, the Magiſtrates were exiled for their libertie, the beginning had a faire gloſe, but the end proued bad: In ſumme all people and nations haue beene deſtroyed by their rebellion, the bookes are ful of their doings, and the memorie thereof will neuer periſh: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O <hi>Holland</hi> take example by them then, accept concord which is offered thee, behold the truth, put off that ougly maſke, behold anothers woundes and heale thy ſelfe.</p>
               <q>A peace ſeeking heart doth find peace euery where.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <head>22.</head>
               <p>WHereupon doeſt thou put thy truſt, and whet thy clawes to ſhew thy ſtrength? doeſt thou thinke no bodie ſhall hinder thee, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhalt vſe thy ſuperiors power, he will at ſome time eſcape, although thou paſſeſt not therefore) and as a Lion ſhew thee his grinning teeth. Of thy great trafficke thou art very proude as though thou onely couldeſt rule the ſame, and make it continue, but no, not ſo, for that ſtands not in humaine power, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in God, who doth it giue and take: that floode would ſoone bee runne dry, thoſe incommes which now doth fill thy Caſſe will ſoon melt, the maine foundation whereon thy common wealth doeth liue is of people diuers of minds and humors, and a variable thréed who ſo thereon doth weaue, ſhalbe ſubiect to many mutations.</p>
               <q>Where the communaltie is mad can be no ſtable eſtate.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:5796:7"/>
               <head>23.</head>
               <p>THy common wealth is vnſtedfaſt, it cannot endure, whom to day they raiſe, to morrow they pull downe: the fauors of the people are neither rockes nor walles, but continually wauering as the leafe by the wind, they will be grieued and become wanton, as then looke for a mutation. They which now raigne and rule, and by their computation ſit faſt, ſhal fall in indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and what then ſhal follow is knowne to God. But this is alwaies the end where ſuch tumultuous people beare any ſway. Is it not better to haue peace, while as yet thy caſe ſeemes ſure and ſtable, then to ſtay vntill occaſion doth turne from thée, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune change, according to her variable and euer chaunging vſe.</p>
               <q>When one ſtayes too long the ſore waxeth incurable.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <head>24.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Hollandia</hi> that féedeſt thy ſelfe with ſtrife and contention, and blindly loueſt warre and trouble, wee admoniſh thée, and God ſhews thee tokens to the end thou ſhouldſt riſe out of this entangled net to thine owne good, why doſt thou hate peace? why doſt thou ſhed the blood of thy brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? what are we Barbarians, man-eating Caniballes or heathens forſaken of God? Oh no, but thinke that thou doeſt it for chriſtians, thy owne country men and neereſt friends: driue <hi>Mars</hi> from hence, and let vs with a chriſtian like mind, knit our forces, ſtrength and treaſures together, let vs oppoſe our ſelues againſt Gods enemies in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> where now Chriſtendome proſpereth, and driue out the Turke, who intendes to deuour vs: there is a rightfull warre and well founded.</p>
               <q>He fightes well who Gods prayſe doth exalt.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>25.</head>
               <p>LEt <hi>concordia</hi> deſcend, let the fire bee quenched which euery where flameth. <hi>Diſcordia</hi> doth ſell her baite deare: we can find no liking in her, a louely vnion would pleaſe vs far better then
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5796:7"/>
thus to drinke <hi>Mars</hi> his bittter reuenge. Come <hi>Holland,</hi> ceaſe thy ire, the ſwéet Doue preſents vnto thy hands an Oliue branch. In peace is ioy, reſt and eaſe: in peace we ſhall become amiable. The warre makes all thinges féeble and weake: Peace féeds and heales: diſcord and contention doth baniſh all good: Peace bréedes good ſucceſſe, vnion and loue. Come O <hi>Holland,</hi> let peace ſhine, for in ſure peace conſiſtes thine and my ſafety.</p>
               <q>Where peace dwels good lucke is manifold.</q>
            </div>
            <trailer>All is well that ends well.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <head>The Hollanders Anſwere to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced Prouinces vpon the rehearſed Admonition.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the bloody warre doth deſtroy and ſpoile all things, and that the ſwéet peace is a great treaſure and highly eſtéemed, that know I better then thy ſelfe, although thou admoniſh me. But ſithence that peace is ſo much by thee deſired, why then doeſt thou not preach the ſame vnto thy Idoll <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who what with hanging, ſtrangling, murthering, and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, deſtroyeth (in a manner) all the worlde, as to all is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, for he continually doth not only plague me, but alſo <hi>Barbary,</hi> the Eaſt and weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> him you do not correct, but allow it all, whereby we manifeſtly ſee that among the meat which thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereſt, vs, is mixed mortall poyſon, which with reaſon wee hate: warie conſideration ſhewes and explaines me thy meaning, and that thou ſeekeſt nothing els but to hang a nette ouer our heades, thou haſt at more times deceyued my ſubiects: thou ſhalt not as now effect any thing, for we know thy old trickes.</p>
               <q>Know ye that it is bad taking one Foxe with an other.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:5796:8"/>
               <head>2.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Yet all peace is not good, for a fained peace which ſhould be hurtfull, or which might cauſe loſſe of lawfull liberty or priuiledges a rightfull war is to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red before ſuch a peace.</note>THe laudes of a true peace I cannot enough pronounce: my pen is too quicke, my tongue too vnſkilfull: one that were far more enriched, yea with heauenly ſkill were not able enough to expreſſe the ſame. All places in the world are ſeene (through peace) to farewell and the countries to flouriſh. A right peace defendeth both the land and people from trouble: an vnfained honorable peace is the beſt thing that one can deſire, but thinke not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that I will with thee conſent to accept any peace, as if they were all in one degree: No, I aſſure my ſelfe, that any war to withſtand an enemie is both laudable and honorable, and to the contrarie ſome peace hurtfull and nought: warres vndertaken for honorable cauſes tending for himſelfe and his, their goodes or life, for freedome or in defence of Gods lawes are honorable, but peace which threatens the loſſe of all theſe may (with right) be refuſed: againſt ſuch one may make a rightfull warre.</p>
               <q>Tis an accurſed peace which deſtroyes Gods word.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Which peace is good and to be deſired.</note>WHen peace doth free from care and trouble, when ſhe diminiſheth the daungers and perilles, when by her meanes great coſts and charges are forborne: when ſhe yeeldeth quiet and tranquillitie of life and minde: as then it is a holy worke to make peace with our enemie. But when as one ſtandeth in doubt and feare,<note place="margin">Which peace is nought and to be ſhunned</note> leaſt vnder the peace her faire vaile lie not hidden ſome ſecrete miſchiefe, then ſhe is mortall venome mixed in a wholeſome potion. One ought alwaies to be bent to peace, (ſo farre forth ſhe be cleare from deceit and daunger) we are naturally giuen to ſeeke peace, but not in ſuch ſort that ſhe ſhould be worſe then the warre: for without ſecuritie of life goodes and conſcience what is it? That the name of peace ſhould onely bee vnto vs a deceitfull pleaſure: a peace whereby one doth leeſe freedome and libertie is a deteſtable plague in the eares of the wiſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5796:8"/>A rightfull warre is better then a faigned peace.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4</head>
               <p>WHerefore we haue here wiſely to conſider if it bee not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mageable to make peace with euery one, if that with procuring a peace we ſubuert not our ſelues into an eternall ſlaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, in ſuch ſort that wee had better to endure the warre, then to liue in a peace which bréedes ſeruitude.<note place="margin">Many haue by warres wonne their libertie, &amp; maintained the ſame: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by bad peace haue made ſlaues, A true libertie is to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red aboue life.</note> Thou ſheweſt vs the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſters of the peace with many examples, as if with (truſting ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) did ſeeke after it, but yet many haue in chooſing peace won their welfare and exiled tiranny: others haue through peace loſt their libertie, and through their light beliefe béene made ſlaues. Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is the chiefeſt thing during ones life, her we ought with our life to maintaine: in the defence of life and goods one will endaunger himſelfe, but yet aboue all, libertie is to be preferred.</p>
               <q>It is honor to expoſe his life in defence of his libertie and patrimony.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5</head>
               <p>IN the defence of our libertie and ſecuritie,<note place="margin">Which to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the war were enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; to keep them they muſt be contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the grace of God a good iſſue. Saguntines. Athens. Our deſire of peace hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies appeared but hath been but badly recompenſed.</note> which wee will not miſſe: we are altogether zealouſly bent, which our burning zeale ſhall not be quenched, nor is there any one in that reſpect, which ſhall turne our minds, we hate them with our hartes which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contrarie vs: we fight couragiouſly and willingly, the armes ſhall not eaſily be pulled out of our handes, neyther yet doe we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in bloodie battailes, we hope the beſt, being alwaies readie rather to abide the hardeſt brunt, then to bee made ſlaues. The noble Saguntines, haue in ſpite of their foes rather choſen to die by famine and miſerie, then by a ſlauiſh peace to ſaue their liues. The Athenians too weak for the might of the Barbarians, haue rather ſuffred their cittie to bee ouerthrowne and ſpoyled, then to be brought vnder their ſubiection.</p>
               <q>An honourable death is to bee preferred before a ſlauiſh life.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:5796:9"/>
               <head>6.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The treatiſe of peace at Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da was dearly bought by thoſe of Buere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Leerdam. Ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, Shoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houen, and Zieriezee. The pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gaunt was of the Spaniſh ſide moſt treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly viola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, as it was concluded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe was made as apeared by diuers letters. By meanes of the treatiſe of peace of Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, was Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricht, Artoys, Haynalt, and Flaunders, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and rent from the other vnited prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; broght again vnder the Spaniſh yoke. Anno 88 whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Armado all ſeemd to be conquered, as then the peace was alſo ſpoken of. Anno 94. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Erneſtus ſo flatteringly, profferd peace by Ieronimus Coema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, and Otto Hartius.</note>THat I haue ſought to bring all things to an vnfained peace, hath appeared by my peaceable dealing: but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt alwaies, ſought (vnder thy peace) to couer deceit. In the treatiſe of peace at <hi>Breda,</hi> appeared thy deceitfull trickes. <hi>Bueren Leerdam, Ouwater, Shoonhouen,</hi> beare yet the markes of thy peace: Immediatly after <hi>Ziericzee</hi> was beſet. The pacification of <hi>Gaunt</hi> thou didſt violate: thy pretence appeared by the letters of <hi>Eſcouedo.</hi> Alſo by the letters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Baro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Selles</hi> which he brought with him at <hi>Mechelen,</hi> from the Spaniſh counſaile. The violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Don Ian</hi> againſt honor, oath and law manifeſtly appeared: it may be ſaid without feare, that nothing but treaſons and ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were intended in all thy faire ſhewes of peace, ſtretching to the annulling and exiling of the vertuous. Tis in vaine, thy faultes are no more to be fauoured.</p>
               <q>But vntruth hath yet hitherto paid his mayſter.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>7.</head>
               <p>HOw deceitfull, ſhamefull, &amp; pernicious was the treatiſe of peace of <hi>Cullen</hi> vnto me, the time hath taught. The ſiege of the good Citie of <hi>Maſtricht</hi> with many other ſubtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices haue alſo bewrayed the ſame, <hi>Artoys</hi> and <hi>Henalt</hi> with others were thereby ſeduced. The dealing with <hi>Flaunders</hi> (to my loſſe) and to what peace thou and thine were inclined, when the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> proffered peace to her Maieſtie, was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ſhewed by the Spaniſh Fleete. More what peace <hi>Erneſtus</hi> brought who ſought to murther his excellencie, as if there by all matters might be pacified. More, the heade of the Inquiſition, Lieuetenant vnto thy holy father, (yea when it was leaſt ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) ſheweth his cruell nature, which (not a yeare agoe) buried a ſilly maiden aliue.</p>
               <q>A foole is he that will be a ſlaue if he may chuſe.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:5796:9"/>
               <head>8.</head>
               <p>IF ſo it were that we deſired peace, yet there is no meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the ſame of the Spaniard, the ground and foundation of truth to bind peace, dependeth on the faith, this may not be forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: without faith or truſt no accorde is to bee made which one may truſt on, or that will dure, or ought to forbeare any alliance with thoſe which kept not their word, faith, nor oath: feare of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe cauſeth an vnquiet minde. The faith is the onely thing whereon peace muſt be built, and where ſhe is abſent (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we ought to build) we muſt like an Oxe ſtande in feare of the axe: this is euen the true expoſition thereof. Let the peace defend vs from the euils preſent and to come, for by a broken peace, to run againe to the warres it falles crueller then before, and brings farre more griefe and trouble.</p>
               <q>Alliance without truth, breeds feare of life and goods.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>9.</head>
               <p>NO Wolues Beares, Lyons, nor Tygers neuer ſo ouer cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell are not ſo pernicious as vnfaithfulneſſe, for if ſo bee that they intend to aſſaile any one they will roare and bray: before the wracke the ſea and tempeſt will toſſe the ſhippe to and fro,<note place="margin">Perfidie is the higheſt miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe in mens dealing.</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it raynes the cloudes will frowne: but vnfaithfulneſſe ſéekes by all ſubtill and deceitfull meanes and faire ſhewes to couer the intended miſchiefe, thereby to draw his allyes into danger. There is nothing more perillous then an enemie ſuppoſed a friend, for we are carefull of our known foes, with armes, regard &amp; watch to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent them. Alſo courage, vnitie, &amp; inuincible ſtrength aſiſt vs, but the enemie who is a ſuppoſed friend,<note place="margin">Embden.</note> hath meanes to miſchieue vs both night and day. <hi>Embden</hi> is our glaſſe by which we haue ſéen what lurketh vnder falſe friendſhip.</p>
               <q>Wiſe is he who by his countries harme is taught foreſight.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>10.</head>
               <p>THe Spaniards peace are méere lies and deceit,<note place="margin">It is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make a firme &amp; true peace with the Spaniard.</note> a very <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſſe wherewith they ſeeke to betray vs, yea euen the peace which <hi>Ioab</hi> gaue <hi>Amaſa,</hi> euen ſo they intend w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faire words to ruine vs. Thou that ſeekeſt peace giueſt vs occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe thy peace, It appeareth by thy reaſons, though they are cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly couered: for thou praiſeſt thy prince to be full of mercie, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5796:10"/>
his lappe is open, his goodneſſe readie. But thou ſayeſt preſently after: If he were cruell and ſeuere, it were no maruell, for he hath reaſon, being that we are cauſe of our owne hurt. This is enough, we are content: but ſooner ſhall heauen and earth be ioyned, ſooner ſhall water and fire (through arte) be mixed together, then I will enter into ſuch peace with thee, which would in no way be benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall vnto vs.</p>
               <q>He that ſees another burne, let him beware of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>indging.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>11.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt proofe. The vſe of princes.</note>THis I proue by the nature and vſe of many Princes: the olde aduentures and experiences doe alſo teach the ſame, that they ſhould neuer enter into alliance or make peace, vnleſſe wee know it to be to their furtherance and profit, that alſo they ſhoulde not keepe the ſame no longer (without brabling) then it ſhoulde be to their good and profite. <hi>Machiauell</hi> their maiſter doeth alſo giue this precept,<note place="margin">Machiauels doctrine. Iulius Ceſar.</note> that any promiſe which a prince might haue made, he neede not to hold, if hee find any damage thereby. <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> alſo vſed to ſay, if one may breake a promiſe or a right againſt any liuing,<note place="margin">Lyſander.</note> one may do it to gouerne or rule. This is alſo <hi>Lyſanders</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion: with bables (ſaith he) one deceiues children, but thoſe of ryper yeares and iudgement with oathes, eyther to reuenge an iniurie, or to hinder and repulſe the intent &amp; might of ones enemy.</p>
               <q>Great truſt giues the faithleſſe meanes to work miſchiefe.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>12.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iulius Pope.</note>
                  <hi>IVlius</hi> the ſecond of that name Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> ſaid that neither with Spaniards, Dutch, or Wallons (whom hee named <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baros</hi>) he neuer did enter into peace, but onely to withdrawe them backe out of <hi>Italie. Maximillian Phillips</hi> grandfather was alſo wont to ſay,<note place="margin">Maximilian.</note> that hee neuer made peace with the French but to reuenge his former wrongs, which hee ſuppoſed to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.<note place="margin">Antiochus Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtris decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Ieruſalem by falſe peace.</note> We find how <hi>Antiochus Illuſtris</hi> with a deceiptful intent made peace with the Iewes, and immediately after ſent his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Apollonius,</hi> who vtterly deſtroyed and burned <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>: the people he made captiues, and conſtrained them to forſake their God. Thoſe which circumciſed themſelues, hee croſſed &amp; murdred, the women he ſtrangled, and killed the children about their necks.</p>
               <q>Miſtruſt is the beſt weapon againſt tyrants.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:5796:10"/>
               <head>13.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANtiochus Empator</hi> through the counſaile of <hi>Lyſias</hi> beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and begirt the ſame with his troupes:<note place="margin">Antiochus Empator de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued the Iewes by falſe peace.</note> but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing he ſhould not take the ſame by force, he ſought to deceiue them with a falſe peace, makes an agréement with them, permits them to vſe their lawes and religion with their libertie, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing entred the citie, he neither reſpected oath nor honor, but cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the walles and fortreſſes of the Cittie to bee pulled downe. Through his command was many a man drowned, captiued,<note place="margin">Alcimus to his owne kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</note> and murthered. <hi>Alcimus</hi> did great miſchiefe in murthering &amp; ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, when he deſired peace with his owne linage, hee being of the Tribe of <hi>Aron,</hi> no harme was ſuſpected in him, in ſomuch that this great truſting hath béene deere vnto the Iewes.<note place="margin">Tryphon. Ionathan.</note> 
                  <hi>Ionathan</hi> had neuer béene betrayed by <hi>Tryphon,</hi> had hee not giuen credit to his words, but ſhould rather haue prepared himſelfe to the combat with him.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Vnwiſe is he who by peace expeecteth any good of the wicked.</hi>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>14.</head>
               <p>THat we haue reaſon to feare can we farther explain,<note place="margin">A more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular vſe of Princes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their ſubiectes.</note> in that a mighty prince or potentate being diſpleaſed with his ſubiects; and muſt fauour them for ſome occaſion, cannot wholly depoſe his wrath, but wel diſſemble the ſame for a while: inſomuch that when he finds oportunitie there is no puniſhment, no reuenge, ſo vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull or cruell, which is badde inough (in his opinion) for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer committed offence: and although he ſweare to keepe inuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the peace, yet ought one neuertheleſſe to feare, becauſe who now keep their word ſo little as princes to their ſubiectes, for they eſtéeme it a ſmall matter, being we ſée they ſeldome make peace with them (being in contention) vnleſſe they be thereto (by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame neede) compelled. Then followes (as they eſtéeme) that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny oath taken through compulſion may be broken when they wil. And to verifie this, we cannot find any example that a prince, who though he haue neuer ſo ſolemnely ſworne truce.</p>
               <q>But finding oportunitie hath not reueng'd his wrong.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>15.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LOdouicus</hi> the ſeconde King of <hi>France,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lewes the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</note> was forced to conclude and make a peace with his ſubiects which had depoſed him, the which he ſolemnely ſwore, but yet afterwards hee made them all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5796:11"/>
ſubtilly away. The Duke of <hi>Nemours, Burgundie,</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniac</hi> loſt their liues, yea hee was ſo much bent to reuenge, that he poiſoned his owne brother <hi>Charles:</hi> A kings crueltie cuts all through,<note place="margin">The king of Feza.</note> and nothing can reſiſt the ſame. The King of <hi>Feza</hi> being lately beſieged by his younger brother was compelled to craue a peace, the communaltie obtayned reaſonable conditions betweene both, whereunto they were ſworne. The king being eſcaped this danger, his brother comming to embrace him, he ſtrangled him &amp; cauſed him to be caſt out of the window. Many one thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſecure when he is in moſt daunger.</p>
               <q>Vnder the greeneſt graſſe lurks the moſt venomous ſnake.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>16.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Henry the 6.</note>
                  <hi>HEnry</hi> the ſixt of that name King of <hi>England,</hi> was forced to make an agréement with <hi>Rychard</hi> Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he firmely ſwore &amp; promiſed the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> and his heires the ſucceſſion of the crowne after his death, but notwithſtanding all that, hee was afterwardes ſlaine in the fielde by the kinges procurement.<note place="margin">Anthonius Caracalla.</note> 
                  <hi>Anthonius Caracalla</hi> in reuenge of ſome flout or mockerie done to him, by ſubtill practices put to death all the youth of <hi>Alexandria</hi> in a place where they were aſſembled, not doubting of any ſuch miſchiefe. <hi>Ferdinandus</hi> of <hi>Arragon</hi> alſo broke his oath,<note place="margin">Ferdinandus.</note> and promiſe done vnto his nobles who had conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt him, for hee cauſed them all ſecretly to bee made away, although notwithſtanding diuers Princes were as ſureties vnto the ſaid promiſe.</p>
               <q>It is bad going as a gueſt vnder ſureties into a Lions denne.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>17.</head>
               <p>THe mercy which we are to expect, ſhould 100. yeares after the day be bemoaned by our ſucceſſors,<note place="margin">An eſpeciall cauſe why of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes we expect neither pardon, nor obliuion of our factes.</note> for they eſteeme vs worſe then Iewes, heathens, or Turkes, yea we are all condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to loſe both our liues and goods, for we haue rent the yoke of the tyrant from our neckes, and haue openly taken armes againſt him, his falſe idolatry we haue exiled, and wholly changed the ſame according to the ſcriptures: renounced the king, &amp; proclaimed him an enemie, as the cruell Spaniſh broode which hath ſworne our ſpoile: againſt the Inquiſition no meanes haue beene ſpared, and all done what was poſſible to ſmother their crueltie. Wee haue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5796:11"/>
choſen other Potentates, this is treaſon to his Maieſtie in the higheſt degrée: wherefore we aſſure our ſelues that all hope of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is loſt, &amp; that thou ſéekeſt to deceaue vs with thy ſwéet words.</p>
               <q>He that belieues eaſily, is cauſe of his owne harme.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>18.</head>
               <p>WHat beliefe or faith ought to be held vnto them who haue ſinned ſo groſly,<note place="margin">An example of his deedes and nature, Granada.</note> what pardon we ſhold haue (God be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) we know it is a mockerie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou telleſt vs our offences ſhall be pardoned, by them who are more inclined to reuenge then pardon: we remember how pittifully <hi>Granada</hi> was vſed, the inhabitants exiled, and the countrie planted with Caſtilians, their goods con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated and themſelues made ſlaues, going with a marke burnt in their foreheades.<note place="margin">Arragon.</note> Alſo how he handled <hi>Aragon</hi> againſt the lawes and priuiledges of the ſame wherunto he was ſworne, he condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the right, ſlayeth it as a foe, as ſoone as hee had got the lande in his poſſeſſion: marke but the couenantes whereunto the countrie had ſworne him, and how they were performed to many a ones griefe: he that will not learne by all theſe examples, let him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelfe to die or to be made a ſlaue.</p>
               <q>A reuengefull harte reſpecteth not honor nor oth to haue his will.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>19.</head>
               <p>HE that moſt will ſeeke to know the kings kinde, let him ſée what ſeruants he vſeth, and let him call their valiant déeds to mind, and what commiſſioners of his haue beene in this country, <hi>Granuelle, Vergas, Roda,</hi> and the Duke <hi>D'Alba</hi> their maiſter in crueltie: <hi>Don Ian</hi> with <hi>Eſcouedo,</hi> and others which were not to be glutted with blood, and were (without faith, truth, or honor) prompt to ſpoile, robbe, burne and deſtroy. <hi>Don Ian</hi> ſaid that a king were fitter to inherit woods, trées mountains, beaſts, water or other ſenceleſſe things, then to be Lord of a mightie countrie, wherein he ſhould ſuffer ſo much as one rebell, or any one of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary religion, which at his pleaſure hee might not put to death. The Marquiſſe of <hi>Kiſbrooke</hi> had rather flowen (with his) to the Diuel then to leaue perſecuting the Heretikes: that they had ſuch intents they were not aſhamed to ſhew not onely in this country, but through all the world.</p>
               <q>The man doth purpoſe, but God doth diſpoſe.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:5796:12"/>
               <head>20.</head>
               <p>THe Weſt Indians much commend the Spaniard, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it appeares by the countrie, which was wont like an Ant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to abound in people, which now by the Spaniards bloody handes are all murthered, falling on them without reaſon or occaſion: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe few yeares they ſtrangled &amp; murthered aboue 180. times hundreth thouſand liuing ſoules. In <hi>Caſtile</hi> are not by the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand part ſo many bloodthirſtie roagues, as in the lande guiltleſſe haue béene ſmothered: who euer heard of more horrible crueltie, no tongue ſo learned that can fully ſet forth the ſame. He that deſireth to know further hereof, let him reade <hi>Bartolomeus de las Caſas,</hi> who writes that they haue rent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infants from the breaſts of their mothers, taking them by the legs daſhed out their braines againſt the ſtones, cut in péeces and throwne to the dogges: many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drethes haue béene by the dogges deuoured, many roſted, ſodde, &amp; inhumanely deuoured.</p>
               <q>The commemoration hereof would wound a ſtony heart.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>21.</head>
               <p>IF yet thy king eſtéeme his honor aboue reuenge, yet in his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion he will neuer budge,<note place="margin">His religion.</note> which concludes (as by the counſayle of <hi>Conſtance</hi> was decréede, whereon wee ought to conſider) that one néedes not kéepe any oath vnto Heretickes: this giues vs oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion enough to miſtruſt, for though the king had ſworne vnto vs a thouſand oaths,<note place="margin">An. 1080.</note> when it pleaſeth the Pope (on whom more then on God they truſt) he may be diſcharged of his oath. Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi> the 7. was the firſt that made this law againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, who diſpleaſing him, hee put him in the banne,<note place="margin">The Biſhops of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nts and Cullin.</note> and egged and incited <hi>Rodolphus</hi> of <hi>Swaben</hi> againſt him, after he had giuen him a diſpenſation of the oath, which the ſaide <hi>Rodolph</hi> had done to the Emperour. But ſo it happened y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the conflict <hi>Rodolphus</hi> loſt his right hand, wherefore he ſaid vnto the Biſhops his counſaylors: Lo there Gods iuſt puniſhment wee not reſpected. There lies now the hand which ſwore homage vnto <hi>Henry</hi> my true Lord.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>It is loſt labour to ſeek to deceyue God.</hi>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <head>22.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Tom. 3. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil. fol. 860.</note>THe counſaile of <hi>Conſtance</hi> not onely concluded, to keepe no faith vnto Heretickes, but moreouer conſtrained and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5796:12"/>
to breake, rent and annullate the ſworne oath. It appeareth by the Emperour <hi>Sygiſmundus</hi> who was very loath ſo ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to breake his oath, done to the king <hi>Laodiſlaus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohannes Hus Ieronimus de Praga. Eccius in Lutherum, counſailes the Emperour to breake his oth in putting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to death.</note> 
                  <hi>Hus</hi> &amp; <hi>Prage</hi> contrary to and againſt his ſafeconduct were throwne in the fire. <hi>Eccius</hi> practiſed alſo to vſe thoſe tricks againſt <hi>Luther</hi> in <hi>Worms</hi> as aboue is ſaid, maintaining theſe decrées very ſtoutly to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours preiudice, that hee ſhoulde retire his giuen conducte, yea more that he was bound to do it by the councles decrée, if he would be reputed a true ſonne vnto the holy Church. The Spanyard is named thus, as in pardons are ſéene, hee being very obedient to worke after that order.</p>
               <q>One refraines often from euill through diligent conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <head>23.</head>
               <p>BY this Conſtantiſh and holy fathers decrée,<note place="margin">Iulianus,</note> was the Cardinal <hi>Iulianus</hi> ſent into <hi>Hungarie</hi> to giue knowledge vnto <hi>Iohan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Huniades</hi> that he might break the truce betwéen the Turks: from which thing he woulde fayne haue refrained as vnlawfull, for hee reſiſted the ſame a great while, but was by the Councell forced, wherefore he refuſed the Turkiſh peace. The Hungarians began the warres very ſtoutly: but the Turkes greatly diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with that faithleſſe déede, aſſembled a mighty hoaſt, with which they fell in <hi>Hungarie</hi> like hungry Wolues, beating al the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans wholly out of the field. There died the Cardinall and <hi>Laodiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lao:</hi> here it appeared that vnto them, &amp; not vnto God their faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe behauiour is a pleaſure, for hee that brake the ſworne truce, truſting on his ſtrength in ſtead of hoped victory they had a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſcomfiture.</p>
               <q>Vntruth and pride neuer remaine vnpuniſhed.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <head>24.</head>
               <p>SEcondly this is a Maxime of the Papall doctrine that one may do euill if good procéed thereof,<note place="margin">The ſecond part of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Ieſuites.</note> eſpecially if it be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furtherance of the holy Church, and enterpriſed to that end, the Ieſuites thoſe murtherers of Princes, ſay and affirme, that one may bereaue kings, princes, and Lords of their liues, diſſemble any manner of way to deceaue the Heretickes, &amp; that any euil is good, ſo it procéed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5796:13"/>
of a good intent.<note place="margin">Thirdly the Popes autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</note> Thirdly ſuch might is giuen to the Pope, that he can binde and vnbinde any thing which is in the compaſſe of the worlde, that is, hee may caſt downe or raiſe Empires and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and diſcharge or keepe oathes: the Pope is all aboue all, hee may alwaies aboue and againſt right doe what hee will: hee hath the right of the king of kinges, for no man how great ſoeuer may ſay,<note place="margin">The Canon.</note> why doeſt thou ſo.</p>
               <q>The Pope (with you) is no man, but a God on earth.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>25.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The faithleſſe neuer wants occaſion.</note>FInally the perfidious (when hee eſpies oportunitie to reuenge his wronges) whereunto they are generally addicted, wantes no excuſes and occaſions to breake his oath. They will kéepe their oathes in ſmall matters, to the ende, that when time ſerues, they may through their diſſimulations worke their will the better: this was ſhewed vnto <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> by <hi>Fabius,</hi> ſaying didſt thou not once truſt to <hi>Syphacius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The counſell of Fabius.</note> and <hi>Numidis,</hi> let it be a warning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée not to be deceaued againe: for the trothleſſe keeps his word and oath in ſmall thinges, thereby the better to attaine the good o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of euery one, by the which he may with leſſe perill &amp; more profite worke his treaſon. Hee then that refuſeth Gods manifeſt aide againſt the ſword, muſt be ſeene to bee deceyued with the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue branch and faire ſhew of peace.</p>
               <q>Once deceyued one hath the more cauſe alwaies to miſtruſt his foe.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <head>26.</head>
               <p>OVt of theſe aboue written examples and reaſons, is to bee perceyued, that <hi>Holland</hi> and her allies are well informed and reſolued not to enter into peace ſo vnaduiſedly with the proud Spaniard, but continually miſtruſt his wonted treacherie; the more hauing conſidered that many nations haue been through their eaſie belieuing and too much truſting deceiued, and almoſt ſpoyled: others to the contrarie, miſtruſting, and by their diligent foreſight haue eſchued their approching perilles, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued their libertie, and defended their common wealth: it is bad to ſtand at anothers mercie, &amp; eſpecially of his enemies who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one hath
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5796:13"/>
iniured <hi>Magdenburge,</hi> and <hi>Rochel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Magdenburge Rochell.</note> choſe rather to dye in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of their libertie, then to truſt to thoſe which are wicked by nature, whereby they haue preſerued themſelues, who elſe were now ouerthrowne.</p>
               <q>Through ſtedfaſtnes the Crown of victorie is wonne.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <head>27.</head>
               <p>THe Admirall of <hi>France</hi> had he not reiected the many aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſementes and counſels giuen him,<note place="margin">The Admirall of France tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to the many oathes of the king was with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands pittifully mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thered. Parthes Arta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus.</note> he had not beene ſo pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully murdred: the diſſimulations of <hi>Charles</hi> the 9. had not beene ſo hurtfull vnto him: at <hi>Paris</hi> had not happened ſuch a maſſacre where the ſtreets were ſtrawed with murthered bodies of 10000. Proteſtantes, beſides many thouſandes in other Cities: Who would not abhorre ſuch crueltie, and rather chooſe an honorable war, before ſuch treacherous agreements. Had <hi>Artabanus</hi> not put too much confidence in his enemie, the Parthians had not béene by <hi>Baſcianus Caracalla</hi> ſo cruelly murthered, had hee not geuen conſent to the match of his daughter, hee had protected the people from that deſtruction for when <hi>Caracalla</hi> more like an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie then a frende, with his men came for his bryde, the Parthians comming in amiable ſort, weaponleſſe to receiue him, hee in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fell with his men vpon them, <hi>Artabanus</hi> hardly eſcaped, he ſaw his people maſſacred.</p>
               <q>The vnexperienced muſt often times learne to their damage.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>28.</head>
               <p>THe plagues which thou prepoſeſt vnto vs, which thou ſayeſt fel vpon theſe which ſcorn peace, we neyther expect nor feare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe that the eſtates nor cauſes of ſuch as thou nameſt are not to be compared to ours, the example which thou ſheweſt vs of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> is without ſence, and not any way to the purpoſe;<note place="margin">Iulius Ceſar. Example ſhewing alſo that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt potentates ought to keep themſelues within their owne lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, and to know God.</note> for <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſought (through ambition) to be chiefe of <hi>Rome,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to bercaue them of their former libertie, he ſought thereby to tranſport (at his pleaſure) the armies into <hi>Italie,</hi> to bring his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie to ſlauerie, yet in the end he bought it with his life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the example is in our behalfe, and ſhewes vs in that as <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> bought his paternity in ſlauery: euen ſo hath done the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſeeking to ſuppreſſe theſe countries, yet God puniſheth his pride, by that little Prouince which he little doubted, inſomuch
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5796:14"/>
that his puniſhment is no leſſe then <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>As the deede is ſo deſerues it like puniſhment.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>29.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Carthage.</note>
                  <hi>CArthage</hi> did often make peace with <hi>Rome:</hi> but they broke it againe, ſetting aſide al honor and oathes, whereat the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines being iuſtly moued, becauſe they eſteemed their oath ſo much, and yet were vſed contrarily, they made towards <hi>Carthage</hi> with all their powers, and recompenced them for their treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: the deede deſerued no leſſe, for falſeneſſe and periury are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly requited with loſſe, and that thou compareſt vs vnto <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridates,</hi> that hath no reſemblance, neither any way <hi>Mith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridates</hi> intendes to ſubuert <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europe</hi> vnder his ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:<note place="margin">Mithridates.</note> murthers many Romains, yea wil ouer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ow <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe, for which cauſe the Romaines with a great hoſt reſiſted him, van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed and puniſhed him accordingly, <hi>Phillip</hi> (like <hi>Mithrida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi>) meant to ouerrunne al the earth, and become a Monarche, ſhall if it pleaſe God finde like fare,</p>
               <q>For they that couet all, commonly looſe all.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <head>30.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iugurtha.</note>EVen as <hi>Iugurth</hi> wrongfully ruled ouer the Numedians, ſo haue <hi>Phillips</hi> Prediceſſors againſt all right tyranized ouer many kingdomes, as <hi>Cicilia, Naples,</hi> the <hi>Indies</hi> and ſuch like, but they ſhall yet with right, withdrawe themſelues from him, yea through Gods iuſt iudgement riſe vp all againſt him, as we with reaſon haue abandoned him, for as it is wonne ſo it will thriue.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sehon.</note>As the Iſraelites deſired <hi>Sehon</hi> to let them paſſe peaceably, and quietly through his land, which he refuſing, the Iſraelites had good occaſion to fal on him &amp; deſtroy him euen ſo haue we onely ſought as obedient ſubiectes according to our paternall right to enioy our libertie, this not onely is refuſed, but alſo thoſe which ſued for the ſame, and many others were ſlaine: This vnmeaſurable crueltie moues and compels vs to reſiſt and hate the Spaniſh broode.</p>
               <q>It is lawfull to reſiſt force, when neceſſitie conſtraines.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <head>31</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Paris.</note>
                  <hi>PAris</hi> moſt trecherouſly bereaued <hi>Menelaus</hi> of <hi>Helena</hi> his dear wife, who firſt in frendſhip was by the Grecians aſked again,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5796:14"/>
but the denyall incited them to anger in ſuch ſort, that they aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled a mighty hoſt, and finally the Troians as they deſerued were ruined: ſo alſo the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhall not eaſily cleare himſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe countries, becauſe he hath rauiſhed our <hi>Helen,</hi> which is our libertie, the which to recouer, we will not feare to aduenture our liues and liuing, vntill the laſt droppe of our bloode, for who would liue content being bereaued of ſo ſweete a bleſſing, and to liue in bondage of life and conſcience? that is no wayes our intent nor deſire, God through his mercy will ſtrengthen vs all in our pretences.</p>
               <q>It is honorable to loue libertie aboue life.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <head>32</head>
               <p>IT is not in our power; nor we may not make any couenant nor peace with our Prince, ſince you name our warre a cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe rebellion, we ought therefore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> belike (as obedient ſubiects) to ceaſe the war, to render al our aduantage, forſake al our right, acknowledge our Superiors againe, ſet our ſelues in the firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, if ſo be we will not taſt the puniſhment due to rebels, wee muſt couch to his command, returne to our old cuſtomes, deliuer vp all the land, giue our Prince power to do and leaue at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, he is our ſuperior, our war is meare wantonneſſe and pride, which we to our power maintaine ſtoutelie and without licence, what all this would be we haue beene taught by the Gallowes, ſword, water and fire, for in the time of obedience thoſe cruelties were vſed, aboue 80000. haue in the Netherlandes beene put to death byforme of iuſtice, onely accuſed of Hereſie.</p>
               <q>This thou nameſt peace, but it is a miſerable ſlauery.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <head>33.</head>
               <p>ANd that our warre is no rebellion, nor madnes, wee manifeſt clearely with cittizenlike and godly lawes, we acknowledge a Lorde, but none that ſhall rule ouer vs in ſuch ſort, that at his pleaſure he ſhall make vs ſlaues, except hee can ſhew and proue that our libertie may be hindred and ſubuerted to ſlauerie at the command of thy king: but this is manifeſt, the people chooſe a Prince: but he ſweares firſt at his crowning, to be vnto them, their lawes and liberties an eternall defendor, and to maintaine them and augment them with all his might, then ſweares the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5796:15"/>
people in recompence of his promiſe to be true to him (ſo far forth he kéepe his oath and worde) hee then that preferres one to an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is more to bée eſteemed, then he that is preferred, although this will ſeeme ridiculous to the flatterers, alſo one which is exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſome eſtate beleeues for ſure that hee that hath raiſed him hath the power in his miſdemeanor to pull him downe againe.</p>
               <q>He that on condition is rayſed, may with condition be abaſed</q>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>34.</head>
               <p>THat the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath not conquered vs with the ſworde (but that he was made Earle vpon condition, wée can eaſily proue, the order of electing or crowning doth ſhew the ſame: for he ſwore firſt to vs, and afterwarde wee to him, wee alſo ſee the manner of the ſwearing in <hi>Arragon</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they elect any one to the kingly eſtate, wee haue alſo choſen thee for our Lord and king on condition,<note place="margin">Trala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> that thou ſhouldeſt keepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolably our rightes and priuiledges otherwiſe not. <hi>Traianus</hi> is alſo of this mind, when he putteth the ſword in the hands of his cheefeſt ruler, ſaying, holde and iuſtly vſe this thy geuenſworde, if in caſe I am valiant and true againſt my enemies in the fielde, but if otherwiſe, vſe it againſt me with al force, hereby follow that when a Prince ſweares, and then goes from his worde, that as then the oath of the ſubiectes is alſo of no worth, but may iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compell and force the Prince to doe iuſtice.</p>
               <q>He that will be truely delt with, muſt firſt be true himſelfe.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <head>35.</head>
               <p>THe Prince that is ſworne to the countries priuiledges to keepe and defend them, not to diminiſh but to augment the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that afterwardes by all ſubtill and deceitfull meanes, will ſpoile the countrie of the ſame: may hee not iuſtly bee declared a Periure of all his ſubiectes, and depoſed from his rule, without that the ſame be accounted rebellion, and eſpecially ſince that our Prediceſſors in their priuiledges concluded (neceſſitie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) neuer to reſiſt their Princes actions, all the while they were iuſt true and good, kéeping their oath, and defended vs as they ought, all that while wée haue obeyed them with life &amp; goodes. as much as any people on earth. The hyſtorie of <hi>Carolus Audax</hi> ſufficiently ſhewes the ſame,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dax.</note> how true and willing his ſubiectes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5796:15"/>
were, ſending him in diuers warres great aſſiſtances of their frée will, and how hée was eſtéemed and loued of little and great.</p>
               <q>It is more ſecurity for a Prince to be loued then feared.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <head>36:</head>
               <p>WHen Kinges will rule ouer conſciences and mindes, and will be obayed, againſt Gods lawes in ſuch reſpect, one may with all godly and worldly right, withſtand them, without therefore vſing any rebellion, whether it be right in Gods ſight to obay you rather then God iudge you,<note place="margin">Act. 4. v. 19.</note> this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared alſo in the Hebrew midwiues, which in the killing of the babes did not effect the kinges command,<note place="margin">Exod. 1. v. 17.</note> Gods mighty hande preſerued <hi>Sydrach, Miſach,</hi> and <hi>Abednago,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daniel 3. v. 28. Dan. 6. v. 16.</note> from the ſcorching flames of fire, becauſe they ſpurned at the kinges command, and truſted in him. And <hi>Daniell</hi> refuſing to offer vnto <hi>Bell</hi> was caſt into the Lyons denne, from the which by Gods miraculous power he was ſaued. <hi>Mathias</hi> with his 5. Brethren reiected the kinges command, nay more raiſed an armie againſt him, God bleſſed their war, prayſed and furthered their pretence, &amp; through his helpe they recouered their freedome.</p>
               <q>Againſt tyranny all God-fearing people may fight.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <head>37.</head>
               <p>SInce this our Prince hath ſought to vſe vs not as good ſubiects but as vanquiſhed ſlaues, nor yet would not ceaſe his perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by no good perſwaſions, nor grant libertie of conſcience, but moreouer ſuch as ſued for it, hath he condemned as Traitors, and put them to death, the countrie being moued, vrged, and forced, through extreame neceſſitie, which according to her priuiledges was lawfull, to procure meanes to diſturbe, and hinder ſuch like tyranny, to liue in her wonted libertie, hath not of any deſire of gaine, nor treacherie, but of meere neede and neceſſity expoſed her ſelfe to the warre, therein following the example of many nations, the which had receiued nothing ſo much iniurie as wee, yet haue they exiled and driuen their Princes away, neither were they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted rebels, nor yet receiued any damage thereby.</p>
               <q>He doth no bodie wrong who defendes his owne right.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <head>38.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EDwarde</hi> the ſecond<note place="margin">Edward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſecond</note> Englandes king through bad counſaile
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5796:16"/>
putteth certaine of his Barons to death, without eyther reaſon or lawful cauſe: but the other Peares of the land moued by that cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aſſembled together an hoaſt of men, tooke him priſoner, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared him vnworthy,<note place="margin">Chriſtern. Tarquinius Superbus. Caius Caligula Nero. Domitianus C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mmodus Maximus.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſtern</hi> of <hi>Denmark</hi> was impriſoned af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he was e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led, and <hi>Tarquinius Superbus</hi> for his cruelty was depoſed by the Romaines the which hee had plagued, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred their gouernement, inſomuch that they diſpleaſed them. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius Caligula</hi> a monſtrous tyrant, was alſo therefore murthered by the Romaines: <hi>Nero</hi> for his filthy and horrible factes was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared a foe, and his life perſecuted, and <hi>Domitianus, Commodus, Maximus,</hi> and more, others of like crueltie were vſed according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for they that ſeeke the ſpoile of the common welth, are alwaies ſeene to buy it deare.</p>
               <q>No Tyrant that euer could eſcape Gods puniſhment.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <head>39.</head>
               <p>BEing then that our warre is no rebellion, as manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, and ſufficiently proued by true examples, and infallible argumentes, thou doeſt vs great wrong to compare vs to rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious <hi>Abſolon,</hi> or to the wicked Iſraelites: for no compariſon can be made of it, we are in no wiſe to ſtand in feare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puniſhment, which rebels haue endured, but ſince wee put our truſt in the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, wee will continually expect a good iſſue of our iuſt quarrell although thou ſeekeſt through thy threates to quench our courages, vanting of thy maiſters Lyonly téeth, with all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſtedfaſtly truſting on our God, thy threates wee let flie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning coniunctly in our intent, eſteeming far better to haue iuſt warre, then a diſſembled peace.</p>
               <q>Who ſo truſts on Gods aide, is neuer put to ſhame.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <head>40.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>IT ſéemes that thou haſt learned the bragging of thy maiſter <hi>Rapſace,</hi> who alſo cryed, wherein doſt thou relie, wherein doſt thou truſt? but what God did, and commanded in the next chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, thou haſt not read or perhaps but badly remembred: hee ſhall not enter the citty, nor endamage the ſame, for I wil defend and kéepe it,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for my ſeruant <hi>Dauids</hi> ſake who truſted in mee, I will protect her againſt the tyrantes pretences, <hi>Baldeus</hi> alſo boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted before <hi>Leidiz,</hi> that one ſhould ſooner touch the ſtarres then
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5796:16"/>
the cittie be reſcued, but God diſpleaſed at this blaſphemie ſent them vnnaturall floodes, whereby his pretence was diſturbed. Thou that through falſe peace ſeekeſt to bring vs in thy net conſider the matter: for if thou art not blinded through thy wilfulnes, thou muſt of force confeſſe that our reſiſtance which thou ſeeſt is no hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane worke.</p>
               <q>God fauoreth our caſe, for the defence of his Chriſt.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="part">
               <head>41</head>
               <p>Aſſure thy ſelfe that I truſt not ſo much on the helpe of my neighbores and allies, as on the iuſt and vpright dealing which we dayly vſe: for when with diligent care I conſider the forepaſſed, and ballance the iſſue thereof, it giues mee a great cauſe of hope, that this will ende wel, and that I ſhal want no meanes, while I feele Gods hand, his bounty, aide, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing which are the infallableſt tokens of a good iſſue of the vnſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtnes thereby, thou makeſt a great diſcourſe, that it hanges in no mens handes, and that it is dayly ſeene, but I know they are ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, and neuer deceiued any, except he diſpleaſed God through our great ſinne: I truſt and beléeue aſſuredlie that they are bound to me, as long as I ſhall with zeale proſecute this iuſt cauſe, and wil through Gods mercy, and in ſpight of the Spaniarde as a yong bud floriſh, which thou with all thy force ſhalt not hinder.</p>
               <q>Gods bleſſing will dwell alwaies faſt with the God-fearing.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <head>42.</head>
               <p>ANd finally when thou comeſt forth with thy Princes power, name him with a common name, becauſe thou knoweſt not thy right: yet for reaſons to your aduantage, doe not name him: neuertheleſſe we perceiue thy deceipt cunningly cloaked there vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as the Aſſe of <hi>Cuma</hi> couered with the Lyons ſkinne: but through his long cares he was knowne: ſo thou alſo with thy peace, masked with a Foxes skinne: we perceiue thy intent: for thou ſheweſt thy maiſter in forme of a Lyon, of whome wee feare to bée deceiued in the end: becauſe wee ſee many footeſteppes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: but none outwarde, whereby is ſeene his malice is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vs: but alſo to them that neuer iniured him, out of thy own wordes we conſtrue his meaning, and what a happy peace wee ſhould haue: we are Lambes, thy Lord a Lyon, thoſe two kindes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5796:17"/>
neuer agree, beſides we are nations of diuers humors.</p>
               <q>Contrary humors doe quicklie breake vnitie.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <head>43</head>
               <p>IF then you, our neighbores, of the ſeduced Prouinces, ſo much and ſo ſeruentlie deſire peace, the way is open, a good ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> peace is at hand, which thou now maiſt attaine, in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our good counſaile, it being impoſſible for you to continue in Peace when you ſhoulde be contracted vnto God with vs: and the proude Spaniarde, open thy eyes, know thy enemie, when thou maiſt driue him away, which through Gods helpe and thy neighbores, may eaſily and in ſhort ſpace bee effected, then peace wil yeelde vs traffick, welfare, and plenty, the peace ſhalbe ſure without falſe ſhew, the more ſince wee are a nation of one kinde and condition, who alſo though to their damage keepe their oath and reſpect their honors, endeauour thou to doe this ridde thy ſelfe from the Spaniſh venime, truſt on Gods mercy, and not on thy kinges great Forces.</p>
               <q>He that puts his truſt in God, neuer comes to ſhame.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="part">
               <head>44.</head>
               <p>IF not, then you Batauians, which haue vndertaken the defence of your priuiledges, let not the feare of death daunt your inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible courages you ſhal not onely thereby recouer infinite praiſe, but alſo hereafter an eternal life: but if you faint, and will ſeeke to ſhunne the perils, you bring your ſelues &amp; your ſucceſſors in great diſquietneſſe: wherefore then take courage, and for the defence of thy patrimony (in recompence that ſhee hath nouriſhed thee) and for your liberty ſpare neither life nor goods, let not any wayes the deſire of this fickle life expel the wonted courages from your hartes, let not the praiſe and renowne of the Battauians) which hetherto hath continued, any way be blemiſhed nor dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, although dangers are at hand, ſhew that this meaning is deepely imprinted in your hartes.</p>
               <q>Farre better to endure a warre that ſhoulde neuer ceaſe, then to be deceiued by a falſe peace.</q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5796:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
